很多涉及到深空旅行的科幻电影中
Watch almost any film involving deep space travel apart from the fantasy ones
你会发现人们从休眠中醒来时
and you'll see people going into or coming out of stasis
苏醒的过程通常看上去非常不愉快
of which the waking up part usually looks quite unpleasant
而这种用于长期太空旅行的诱导休眠技术
but could this type of induced hibernation for longer space journeys
能在不远的将来变成现实吗？
become a reality in the not so distant future.
以我们现有的火箭科技 在太阳系内旅行得越远
The farther we travel in to the solar system with our current transport technology,
花的时间就越长
the longer it takes to get anywhere,
短则去火星的五个月 长则去外行星的10年
from about 5 months to mars up to around 10 years to get to the outer planet
更不用说恒星际旅行了
and that's without even thinking about traveling to the stars.
以我们现有科技 去最近的比邻星要七万年
The nearest Proxima Centauri would take about 70,000 years with our current tech.
其实如果飞船能以光速飞行 就不需要休眠了
因为飞船上的时间会很短
即使我们能以光速旅行 整个旅程也要花四年
Even if we could travel at the speed of light it's over a 4 year journey.
这对于探测器来说没什么 但就像之前说过的一样
This is fine for robotic space probes but as it has been said before,
只要加入了人 那问题可就多了
as soon as you add humans into the mix the issues go up by an order of magnitude.
让人在上面呆上几年
Having people awake a roaming around for years
不但要消耗大量资源来保证维持宇航员的生命
not only takes up much more in the way of resources to feed them and keeping them alive
还会造成精神问题 比如无聊 孤独
but there are the psychological issues of boredom, loneliness
如果有人因此犯罪 还会让狭小的飞船中的人们神经紧绷
and just getting on each others‘ nerves trapped in a small spacecraft
for as long or longer than someones gets for committing a serious crime.
如果我们可以让人类进入一种休眠状态 则会解决很多问题
If we could put people into some form of hibernation it would solve a lot of these issues.
如果旅程多数时间都在睡觉 那居住舱可以做得又轻又小
If they are asleep for most of the journey then the space habitats themselves can also be smaller and lighter
相比全程清醒的乘员 就需要带更少的燃料 更少的发动机
so less propellant and rockets engines are required compared to a fully awake crew.
还能加装更多的防护罩以抵抗宇宙射线
This would also allow more shielding against cosmic radiation which is probably
而这可能才是长期太空飞行的最大问题
the biggest issue for long-duration space flights.
即使对于火星任务 这也会对飞船构型带来巨大改变
Even on a mars mission, it could make a substantial difference to the craft configuration.
人们也希望这能缓解些许失重带来的肌肉萎缩与骨质流失等影响
It's hoped that it could also reduce some of the effects of weightlessness such as muscle and bone loss.
然而 我们不是天生会休眠的物种
However, we are not a naturally hibernating species
我们在生理上也无法适应不靠外界帮助进入任意时长的休眠状态
and we don't have the biological adaptations to enter such state
and stay in it for any length of time without outside help.
我们当前拥有的最接近的技术是低温疗法
The nearest thing we have at the moment is Therapeutic Hypothermia
在某些医疗程序和创伤治疗中很有名
which is well known and used in certain medical procedures and trauma treatments
但这和休眠是不同的
but this is not the same as hibernation.
其他诱导休眠的办法诸如吸入硫化氢气体曾被用于小白鼠
Other methods of inducing torpor such as inhaling Hydrogen Sulfide has been used in mice
可以减少细胞的氧气需求量
to reduce the cellular demand for oxygen
研究当中 小鼠大脑中一组专门的神经元被抑制
and research into inhibiting a specialized group of neurons in the brains of rats
从而阻断其体温调节中比如颤抖之类的冷反射
to block the bodies thermo-regulatory cold defense like shivering
在诱导体温降低的同时还会增加心率
and increasing the heart rate when the body temperature drops are also being conducted.
人类等哺乳动物进化出了独立于外界温度的恒定体温
We humans and other mammals have evolved to have a constant body temperature independent of the ambient conditions.
这在进化上给了我们更大的优势 让我们有更广的活动范围
This gives us an evolutionary advantage for increased mobility
但也让我们有了更快的代谢速率
but it also means we have a high metabolic rate,
我们比休眠的动物需要更多的食物 排出更多废物
we need a lot more food and produce more waste than animals in hibernation.
所以关键是在不损伤机体的情况下减慢代谢速率
Slowing this metabolic rate is the key goal but without causing damage to the body in the process.
动物有两种休眠方式来抵御
There are two types of hibernation which animals use to help them survive conditions
诸如冬天的严寒 干燥 酷热或食物匮乏
such as harsh cold winters, very dry and hot periods or when their seasonable food is unavailable.
这两种状态分别叫真冬眠和昏睡
These two states are true hibernation and torpor.
真冬眠是动物自愿的状态
True hibernation is a voluntary state
动物会提前积累脂肪 之后进入深度睡眠状态
where the animal prepares by building up fat reserves and then goes into a truly deep state of sleep
其间体温、心率、呼吸、代谢速率都会极大降低
whereby the bodies temperature, heart rate, breathing, and metabolic rate all dramatically slow down.
以花栗鼠为例 冬眠时心率可以从每分钟350下降低到每分钟4下
A chipmunk, for example, can lower its heart rate from 350 bpm to just 4bpm during hibernation
很多动物会在这期间消耗身体一半的重量
and many animals can lose up to half their body weight during this time.
昏睡也像是深度睡眠的状态
Torpor is like a very deep sleep state
也会降低体温、心率、呼吸和代谢速率
with the low body temperature, heart rate, breathing and metabolic rate of hibernation
但时长根据物种从一晚到数月不等
but this can last from a normal night sleep cycle to months depending on the species.
黑熊的这个状态有3-5个月 其间会定期醒来
Black Bears enter this state for 3-5 months with regular wake up periods
它们甚至可以循环体内的含氮废物 防止肌肉萎缩
and they can even recycle Nitrogen waste from the bodies, preventing muscle atrophy.
昏睡状态下的动物也能醒来
Animals in a state of torpor can also wake up,
但这可能需要一小时甚至更多 才能让一切恢复原本的速度
though it takes maybe an hour or more to do so and bring everything up to speed.
这两者中 昏睡可能是对我们最有用的
Out of these two, torpor would be most useful for us
因为我们可以在紧急情况下或者计划中随时醒来
because of the ability to wake up in an emergency or on schedule.
但我们仍然不了解这种状态的细胞层面和分子层面的机制
But we still don't know the cellular and molecular mechanisms of natural suspended animation.
人类可以受控进入低体温状态长达14天
People have been kept in a controlled hypothermic state for up to 14 days
但会有严重的副作用
but there are problems with serious side effects
比如血栓 出血 感染 肝脏损伤
such as blood clots, bleeding, infection and liver damage.
还需要有定期的营养与液体维持我们身体正常运转
There is also the need for us to have regular nutrients and fluids keep our bodies working
因为我们没有冬眠动物有的自然适应力
as we don't have the natural adaptations that hibernating animals have
这就是我们面对的最大问题
and this is the biggest problem we face.
NASA和ESA都在研究诱导昏睡
Both NASA and ESA are working on Torpor inducing habitats
给人注射镇定剂后冷却 进入轻微的低体温状态
where the person would be sedated and then cooled, placing them into a mildly hypothermic state.
为了保证营养与液体供应 他们使用了“完全注射营养液”
In order to provide the nutrients and fluids a process called Total Parenteral Nutrition is used.
该技术通过静脉为人体补充所有必需营养物质
This is feeding a person intravenously with all the essential nutrients and fluids to keep them alive
通过类似在外周静脉置入中心静脉导管
with something like a peripherally inserted central catheter.
这可以让营养物质直接进入血液
This provides the nutrients directly into the bloodstream
通常用于各年龄段无法进食的病人
and is regularly used in people of all ages when they can not be fed by mouth.
该过程跳过了进食与消化过程 因为消化系统是未激活状态
The process bypasses the eating and digestive tract which is inactive,
液体会以每小时50毫升泵入体内
with the fluids pumped in at about 50 ml per hour.
这还要采取很多预防措施 比如要让居住舱内尽可能无菌
There would also have to be many precautions taken such as making the inside of the habitat a sterile as possible
并使用隧道导管和抗生素注入活动导管
and using tunneled catheters and antibiotic-infused activity catheters
因为休眠时期任何感染都非常严重 甚至会致命
as any infection occurring during stasis could be very serious or even fatal
而飞船上医疗设备又极少 整个旅程就完犊子了
and they would be very little in the way of any medical aid that could be done during the flight.
但这种低温诱导的休眠有一个问题
But there are issues with this kind of Hypothermic induced "stasis".
虽然身体的代谢速率降低到70% 耗氧量更少
Although the bodies metabolic rate drops by about 70% and uses less oxygen,
大脑却并没有进入睡眠状态 这也是为什么电影中的乘客醒来时会觉得筋疲力尽
the brain never actually goes to sleep, which is why in the film "Passengers" they wake up feeling extremely tired.
新的研究发现睡眠时大脑会排出白天积累的毒素
New research is also finding that during sleep the brain flushes out toxins that build up during the day
而这些毒素是阿兹海默症的诱因
and which are thought to lead to the onset of Alzheimer's disease,
而在休眠中大脑如果没有排毒 则在长期上是个麻烦
which if this doesn't happen in stasis could be a problem for long periods.
经历低温疗法后的病人经常需要几天时间恢复体力与知觉
Patients who currently undergo Therapeutic Hypothermia often take days to regain their strength and awareness,
这对于宇航员来说是不行的 他们需要在几小时内就醒来并对警报作出回应
not the sort of thing that an astronaut needs when they have to be awake and alert in just a few hours.
为了预防肌肉萎缩
To help prevent muscle atrophy,
可以使用很低能量的电脉冲刺激肌群
muscles could be electrically stimulated with very low-level electrical pulses to key muscle groups.
还可以使用机械手操控 管理休眠中的乘员
Robot arms would also be able to manipulate and manage the crew during the time they are in stasis.
又因为居住舱会比醒着的乘员需求的更小
And because the living habitat is smaller than that required for a waking crew,
就可以使用人工重力旋转整个休眠区
artificially-induced gravity could be created by rotating the whole sleeping area.
这个领域还有很多工作要完成
There is a still a lot of work to be done in this field
所以早期的火星任务不太可能会用上休眠技术
so its highly unlikely that it would be used any of the early Mars mission
但一旦这些问题被解决 那它就可能成为火星 甚至更远的任务中的标配
but once the issues have been ironed out it could become a standard way to travel to Mars and beyond.
长达数年的任务可能需要更长的苏醒期
Journeys running into years though would require longer wake up periods
或者轮班制 比如保证总有1/3的乘员是苏醒状态
or a shift rotation where maybe 1/3 of the crew are awake at any one time.
在这个技术成熟之前
By the time this becomes widely available
我们可能已经有了更快的太空旅行技术
we might even have developed quicker ways of getting around in space.
感谢观看 记得看看Curious Droid频道其他视频
So thanks for watching and don't forget to check out some of our other videos if you get the chance
记得关注 点赞 分享~
and please subscribe, thumbs up and share.